=To Kill A Songbird=
=لقتل طائر مغرد=
(Adapted from Shen Xiaoguan's Bird Kills Seven People)
(مقتبس من رواية شين شياو غوان " طائر يقتل سبعة أشخاص")
=Episode 2=
=الحلقة ٢=
(Divine Lady Rescues Drowning New County Magistrate)
(سيدة إلهية تنقذ قاضي مقاطعة جديد من الغرق)
(You're in a rush to leave the sect even though your cultivation is incomplete.)
(أنت في عجلة من أمرك لمغادرة الطائفة على الرغم من أن تدريبك الروحي غير مكتمل.)
(To seek revenge, you cultivated the art of illusion, causing a reverse flow.)
(سعياً للانتقام، مارست فن الوهم، مما تسبب في تدفق عكسي.)
(13 Years Ago) (You must undergo acupuncture)
(قبل 13 عامًا) (يجب أن تخضع للعلاج بالإبر الصينية)
(every day just to stay alive.)
(كل يوم فقط للبقاء على قيد الحياة.)
(Elder Baiyun)
(الشيخ بايون)
(Is it truly worth it?)
(هل الأمر يستحق كل هذا العناء حقاً؟)
(I once believed that Heaven's justice is clear as day.)
(كنت أعتقد ذات مرة أن عدالة السماء واضحة وضوح الشمس.)
(However, my entire clan was massacred)
(لكن عشيرتي بأكملها تعرضت لمذبحة)
(just because my brother was framed.)
(فقط لأن أخي تعرض للتلفيق).
Murderer! Surrender right now!
قاتل! استسلم الآن!
(My brother became a scapegoat.)
(أصبح أخي كبش فداء.)
(He was forced to confess through torture, and he died a wrongful death.)
(أُجبر على الاعتراف تحت التعذيب، ومات ميتة ظالمة.)
(My parents witnessed the incident personally.)
(شهد والداي الحادثة شخصياً.)
(They took their own lives out of rage.)
(انتحروا بدافع الغضب.)
(The villains tried to bury the truth by burning down the place.)
(حاول الأشرار دفن الحقيقة عن طريق حرق المكان.)
(It all started with a thrush.)
(بدأ كل شيء بداء القلاع.)
(My family was shattered overnight.)
(تفككت عائلتي بين عشية وضحاها.)
(And, I became a wandering orphan.)
(وأصبحت يتيماً متجولاً.)
It's you again!
أنت هنا مجدداً!
How dare you steal my buns? I'll beat you to death!
كيف تجرؤ على سرقة كعكاتي؟ سأضربك حتى الموت!
(Since then,)
(منذ ذلك الحين،)
(I could only survive by stealing food.)
(لم يكن بإمكاني البقاء على قيد الحياة إلا عن طريق سرقة الطعام.)
(I was thrashed around like a rodent.)
(لقد تعرضت للضرب المبرح مثل القوارض.)
(And, I almost died.)
(وكدت أموت.)
(But I insisted on surviving.)
(لكنني أصررتُ على البقاء على قيد الحياة.)
(I swore that I would find the mastermind)
(أقسمت أنني سأجد العقل المدبر)
(even if I only had one breath left.)
(حتى لو لم يتبق لي سوى نفس واحد.)
(No matter where or who he is,)
(بغض النظر عن مكانه أو هويته)
(I shall make him fall to the depths of hell,)
(سأجعله يسقط في أعماق الجحيم)
(and make him pay for what he has done)
(وجعله يدفع ثمن ما فعله)
(on my brother's death anniversary.)
(في ذكرى وفاة أخي.)
Since this is the will of fate,
بما أن هذه هي مشيئة القدر،
you may leave.
يمكنك المغادرة.
Your path
مسارك
has only begun.
لم يبدأ الأمر إلا الآن.
But I have a piece of advice for you.
لكن لدي نصيحة لك.
"With a sparrow's frail form, I met my end upon a rock"?
"بجسد عصفور هش، لقيتُ حتفي على صخرة"؟
(With a sparrow's frail form, I met my end upon a rock) Master, are you trying to say
(بجسد عصفور هزيل، لقيتُ حتفي على صخرة) يا سيدي، هل تحاول أن تقول
that if I insist on seeking the truth,
أنه إذا أصررتُ على البحث عن الحقيقة،
I will die at the hands
سأموت على أيدي
of a person whose name is related to rock?
عن شخص اسمه مرتبط بالصخور؟
Shi?
هو؟
Which Shi?
أي شي؟
Naturally, it's Shi, as in beautiful jade and rugged rock.
بطبيعة الحال، إنها شي، كما في اليشم الجميل والصخر الوعر.
(Like a stone met in water.)
(مثل حجر اصطدم بالماء.)
(He occupies a lofty position,)
(إنه يشغل منصباً رفيعاً،)
(yet will surely drag you down into the mire.)
(لكنها ستجرك بالتأكيد إلى الوحل.)
(Are you not afraid?)
(ألا تخاف؟)
Divine Lady?
سيدة إلهية؟
"Divine Lady"?
"سيدة إلهية"؟
This morning, Divine Lady saved me.
أنقذتني السيدة الإلهية هذا الصباح.
What's wrong with me calling her that?
ما الخطأ في أن أناديها بذلك؟
Magistrate Lu, you must be kidding me.
القاضي لو، لا بد أنك تمزح معي.
(Magistrate Lu?)
(القاضي لو؟)
She's a demoness.
إنها شيطانة.
How could she save you?
كيف استطاعت إنقاذك؟
It's like this.
الأمر هكذا.
I fell into the river.
سقطت في النهر.
(Eight Hours Ago, At the Beginning of the Hour of Si)
(قبل ثماني ساعات، في بداية ساعة سي)
(Eight Hours Ago, At the Beginning of the Hour of Si) Shen Guan'er was born into a poor family.
(قبل ثماني ساعات، في بداية ساعة سي) ولد شين غوان إير في عائلة فقيرة.
(Since I assumed my position not long ago,)
(منذ أن توليت منصبي منذ وقت ليس ببعيد،)
(I thought I should be more considerate of the people's circumstances.)
(كنت أعتقد أنه ينبغي عليّ أن أكون أكثر مراعاة لظروف الناس.)
(Therefore, I took a stroll.)
(لذلك، قمت بنزهة قصيرة.)
To raise his children.
لتربية أبنائه.
Mister, what story is the storyteller talking about?
يا سيدي، ما هي القصة التي يتحدث عنها الراوي؟
It's the Thrush Case.
إنها حالة داء المبيضات الفموي.
Have you guys heard about it before?
هل سمعتم بهذا من قبل؟
Liang Andao, also known as Justice Liang,
ليانغ أنداو، المعروف أيضاً باسم القاضي ليانغ،
will come to Huachang County together with Inspecting Envoy Zhai Lu
سيأتي إلى مقاطعة هواشانغ برفقة المبعوث المفتش تشاي لو
in half a month.
في غضون نصف شهر.
As the deal fell through,
بعد فشل الصفقة،
he murdered him out of rage.
قتله بدافع الغضب.
He even chopped off Shen Guan'er's head
بل إنه قطع رأس شين غوان إير
and tossed it into the river.
وألقى بها في النهر.
As the saying goes,
وكما يقول المثل،
what goes around comes around,
ما يدور حولها ويأتي حولها،
and everything has its consequences.
ولكل شيء عواقبه.
The magistrate could distinguish right from wrong.
كان بإمكان القاضي التمييز بين الصواب والخطأ.
In the end, Li Ji ended his own life in prison out of guilt.
في النهاية، أنهى لي جي حياته في السجن بدافع الشعور بالذنب.
(Since I knew how to swim,)
(بما أنني كنت أعرف كيف أسبح،)
(I thought of taking a swim with the great weather and all.)
(فكرت في السباحة مع هذا الطقس الرائع وكل شيء.)
(But the weather was too comfortable.)
(لكن الطقس كان مريحاً للغاية.)
(I actually fell asleep by accident.)
(في الحقيقة، غفوتُ بالصدفة.)
(When I woke up,)
(عندما استيقظت،)
(water had already entered the boat.)
(كان الماء قد دخل القارب بالفعل.)
(Thus, the boat sank.)
(وهكذا غرق القارب.)
Help! Someone's in the water!
النجدة! هناك شخص ما في الماء!
(I fell into the river just like that.)
(سقطت في النهر هكذا تماماً.)
(When I woke up for the second time,)
(عندما استيقظت للمرة الثانية،)
(someone had already rescued me and brought me ashore.)
(لقد أنقذني أحدهم بالفعل وأوصلني إلى الشاطئ.)
(When I opened my eyes,)
(عندما فتحت عيني،)
(the first sight I witnessed)
(أول مشهد رأيته)
(was Divine Lady holding my hands.)
(كانت سيدة إلهية تمسك بيدي.)
Miss only held your collar.
لم تمسك الآنسة سوى بياقة قميصك.
Who said she held your hands?
من قال إنها أمسكت بيديك؟
This morning, we went into town for groceries.
ذهبنا هذا الصباح إلى المدينة لشراء البقالة.
On our way back, my young attendant wanted to go boating on the lake.
وفي طريق عودتنا، أرادت مرافقتي الشابة الذهاب في جولة بالقارب في البحيرة.
That's why we went to the lake.
لهذا السبب ذهبنا إلى البحيرة.
And that's how
وهكذا
I met Magistrate Lu.
قابلت القاضي لو.
I'm sure it's because of my dashing appearance
أنا متأكد من أن ذلك يعود إلى مظهري الجذاب
and innate talent.
والموهبة الفطرية.
Therefore, you took an instant liking to me.
لذلك، أعجبت بي على الفور.
That's why you rescued me, am I right?
لهذا السبب أنقذتني، أليس كذلك؟
Magistrate Lu, don't tell me you became her alibi
القاضي لو، لا تقل لي إنك أصبحت دليل براءتها
all because you fell for the demoness's trick.
كل ذلك لأنك وقعت ضحية خدعة الشيطانة.
Fell for her trick?
هل انخدعت بحيلتها؟
What do you mean?
ماذا تقصد؟
This noon, someone in the western marketplace saw Fan Jili, the victim.
في ظهر هذا اليوم، رأى أحدهم في السوق الغربي فان جيلي، الضحية.
That indicates that he was murdered
هذا يدل على أنه قُتل.
after the hour of Wu and before the hour of Wei.
بعد ساعة وو وقبل ساعة وي.
Could it be that you never closed your eyes
هل من الممكن أنك لم تغمض عينيك أبداً؟
and she never left your side all that while?
ولم تفارقك طوال تلك الفترة؟
You're right.
أنت على حق.
I was giddy after I was rescued.
شعرتُ بفرحة عارمة بعد إنقاذي.
It's not impossible for you to rush back here
ليس من المستحيل أن تعود إلى هنا بسرعة
after murdering the victim.
بعد قتل الضحية.
To think that I treated you with all my heart.
يا للعجب أنني عاملتك بكل قلبي.
But you were deceiving me all along!
لكنك كنت تخدعني طوال الوقت!
This is truly heartbreaking.
هذا أمرٌ مفجع حقاً.
Magistrate Jiang, take her back.
القاضي جيانغ، أعدها إلى مكانها.
Interrogate her immediately.
استجوبها فوراً.
Magistrate Jiang, you said
قلتَ يا قاضي جيانغ؟
the victim's body was found at the western town outskirts.
تم العثور على جثة الضحية في الضواحي الغربية للمدينة.
How long did it take you all
كم استغرق الأمر منكم جميعاً؟
to come here from the western town outskirts?
هل سيأتي الناس إلى هنا من ضواحي المدينة الغربية؟
Three hours.
ثلاث ساعات.
Official Lu woke up at around the hour of Wei.
استيقظ المسؤول لو في حوالي ساعة وي.
If I did murder him at the hour of Wu at the western town outskirts,
لو أنني قتلته في ساعة وو على مشارف المدينة الغربية،
how could I rush back and keep Magistrate Lu company within an hour?
كيف يمكنني العودة بسرعة ومؤانسة القاضي لو في غضون ساعة؟
Magistrate Jiang,
القاضي جيانغ،
Divine Lady is right.
السيدة الإلهية محقة.
She can't just appear out of nowhere.
لا يمكنها أن تظهر فجأة من العدم.
She can't just rescue me and murder the victim at the same time.
لا يمكنها أن تنقذني وتقتل الضحية في نفس الوقت.
I know.
أنا أعرف.
Magistrate Jiang, you're prejudiced against me.
أيها القاضي جيانغ، أنت متحيز ضدي.
But Mr. Fan's death
لكن وفاة السيد فان
has nothing to do with me.
لا علاقة لي بالأمر.
All in all,
بشكل عام،
Divine Lady isn't a suspect.
السيدة الإلهية ليست مشتبه بها.
Magistrate Jiang, this is a huge case.
القاضي جيانغ، هذه قضية ضخمة.
You should follow me back and investigate the case.
يجب عليك متابعتي والتحقيق في القضية.
Do not bother Divine Lady anymore.
لا تزعج السيدة الإلهية بعد الآن.
Come on.
تعال.
Let's go.
دعنا نذهب.
Divine Lady,
سيدتي الإلهية،
we have plenty of time ahead of us.
أمامنا وقت طويل.
Miss, you made a watertight argument.
يا آنسة، لقد قدمتِ حجة دامغة.
I'm sure they won't suspect us.
أنا متأكد من أنهم لن يشكوا بنا.
It's not like the plan was flawless.
لم تكن الخطة مثالية.
It actually has a fatal flaw.
في الواقع، يحتوي على عيب قاتل.
I'm taking a gamble too.
أنا أيضاً أغامر.
On what?
على ماذا؟
On whether the coroner of Huachang County
بشأن ما إذا كان الطبيب الشرعي لمقاطعة هواشانغ
would do an autopsy
سيتم إجراء تشريح للجثة
in seven days.
في غضون سبعة أيام.
Autopsy?
تشريح الجثة؟
The body is all burned up.
الجثة محترقة بالكامل.
Do we still need to perform an autopsy?
هل ما زلنا بحاجة إلى إجراء تشريح للجثة؟
Of course.
بالطبع.
(Cui San, Coroner) But we need to wait.
(كوي سان، الطبيب الشرعي) لكننا بحاجة إلى الانتظار.
We need to wait?
هل علينا الانتظار؟
Wait for what?
ماذا تنتظر؟
There are no coroners in the nearby counties.
لا يوجد أطباء شرعيون في المقاطعات المجاورة.
Any corpse exhibiting unusual characteristics
أي جثة تظهر عليها خصائص غير عادية
within the radius of several miles
ضمن دائرة نصف قطرها عدة أميال
will be sent to my place.
سيتم إرسالها إلى منزلي.
In addition, bandits have been running rampant on Mount Cangyun.
بالإضافة إلى ذلك، ينتشر قطاع الطرق بشكل واسع في جبل كانجيون.
Many people have died.
لقد مات الكثير من الناس.
We have to follow
علينا أن نتبع
the order of things, you know?
ترتيب الأمور، كما تعلم؟
Can't you see
ألا ترى
that the morgue is already full?
هل يعني ذلك أن المشرحة ممتلئة بالفعل؟
Even the kitchen in the side courtyard
حتى المطبخ الموجود في الفناء الجانبي
was used to store corpses.
كان يستخدم لتخزين الجثث.
Mr. Cui, please don't blame me for bothering you.
السيد كوي، أرجو ألا تلومني على إزعاجك.
But I think Magistrate Jiang doesn't like me.
لكنني أعتقد أن القاضي جيانغ لا يحبني.
Not only was he unwilling to ride in the same carriage as me,
لم يكن راغباً فقط في الركوب في نفس العربة معي،
but he also sent me to you.
لكنه أرسلني إليك أيضاً.
But I'll say this first.
لكن سأقول هذا أولاً.
I didn't come here of my own accord.
لم آتِ إلى هنا بمحض إرادتي.
I can forgive the fact that he doesn't know any courtesy.
يمكنني أن أغفر له حقيقة أنه لا يعرف أي أدب.
But as a coroner, you have quite the eccentric temper as well.
لكن بصفتك طبيبًا شرعيًا، لديك أيضًا مزاج غريب الأطوار.
No one in the magistrate's office
لا يوجد أحد في مكتب القاضي
takes me seriously.
يأخذني على محمل الجد.
Hey, the body is all burned up.
يا إلهي، الجثة محترقة بالكامل.
What can you find out from that?
ماذا يمكنك أن تستنتج من ذلك؟
There are things he can find out.
هناك أشياء يمكنه اكتشافها.
For example, the mouth, nose, heart, and lungs.
على سبيل المثال، الفم والأنف والقلب والرئتين.
An experienced coroner
طبيب شرعي متمرس
can tell whether a victim is recently murdered
يمكن معرفة ما إذا كانت الضحية قد قُتلت مؤخراً.
or has been buried for several days
أو دُفن لعدة أيام
at first glance.
للوهلة الأولى.
Unless...
إلا إذا...
Unless what?
إلا إذا ماذا؟
Unless we reduce the body to ashes.
إلا إذا حوّلنا الجسد إلى رماد.
Wait.
انتظر.
What are you burning?
ما الذي تحرقه؟
I'm asking you.
أنا أسألك.
What were you burning just now?
ماذا كنت تحرق الآن؟
A bag of charcoal on top of the furnace.
كيس من الفحم فوق الفرن.
What charcoal?
أي نوع من الفحم؟
That was half of Fan Jili's skeleton!
كان ذلك نصف هيكل فان جيلي العظمي!
Go away!
يبتعد!
It has already been reduced to ashes.
لقد تحولت بالفعل إلى رماد.
What can you tell from this?
ماذا يمكنك أن تستنتج من هذا؟
You...
أنت...
Aren't you afraid that Fan Jili might turn into a vengeful spirit
ألا تخشى أن يتحول فان جيلي إلى روح انتقامية؟
and seek revenge on you at night?
ويسعى للانتقام منك ليلاً؟
I'll say this first.
سأقول هذا أولاً.
I didn't come here of my own accord.
لم آتِ إلى هنا بمحض إرادتي.
Inspect these remains for me.
افحص هذه البقايا من أجلي.
Are there any surviving family members of Li Ji and Shen Xiu?
هل يوجد أي أفراد من عائلة لي جي وشين شيو على قيد الحياة؟
Shen Xiu had a wife and a pair of children.
كان لدى شين شيو زوجة وطفلان.
They passed away a few years ago after contracting the plague.
لقد توفوا قبل بضع سنوات بعد إصابتهم بالطاعون.
Li Ji's entire family perished in the Yuehua Street fire.
لقي جميع أفراد عائلة لي جي حتفهم في حريق شارع يوهوا.
He shouldn't have any family members left.
لا ينبغي أن يكون لديه أي أفراد من عائلته.
any family members left, huh?
أي أفراد عائلة متبقين، أليس كذلك؟
We have to find out who she is.
علينا أن نكتشف من هي.
Otherwise, it might become too chaotic,
وإلا فقد يصبح الوضع فوضوياً للغاية.
and that'll foil our plan.
وهذا سيُفشل خطتنا.
Sir, you're literally a demon of chaos.
يا سيدي، أنت حرفياً شيطان الفوضى.
Why would you be afraid of chaos?
لماذا تخاف من الفوضى؟
Of course I'm afraid of chaos.
بالطبع أنا أخشى الفوضى.
I'm very timid.
أنا خجول جداً.
However, there's no need to rush things.
لكن لا داعي للعجلة.
We're not the only ones
لسنا الوحيدين
who want to stop her advancement.
الذين يريدون إيقاف تقدمها.
(Xuezhao Residence)
(إقامة شيوزهاو)
Water!
ماء!
Give me water!
أعطني ماءً!
Water...
ماء...
You wretch!
يا لك من بائس!
Who exactly are you...
من أنت بالضبط...
You don't remember me, huh?
أنت لا تتذكرني، أليس كذلك؟
That's fine.
هذا جيّد.
I'll make you
سأجعلك
remember every single bit.
تذكر كل تفصيلة.
You'll receive your just deserts!
ستنال جزاءك العادل!
Just deserts?
هل هذا جزاء عادل؟
Everyone dies eventually.
كلنا سنموت في النهاية.
Why the rush?
لماذا هذه العجلة؟
I was just doing it for the money.
كنت أفعل ذلك من أجل المال فقط.
I...
أنا...
I have no idea who he is.
ليس لدي أدنى فكرة من هو.
He gave me a letter.
أعطاني رسالة.
He wanted me to frame Li Ji.
أراد مني أن أدبر مكيدة ضد لي جي.
Who exactly are you?
من أنت بالضبط؟
Try to recall the details
حاول أن تتذكر التفاصيل
of the Thrush Case.
في حالة داء المبيضات.
For every single detail you recall,
لكل تفصيل تتذكره،
I'll give you a bowl of water.
سأعطيك وعاءً من الماء.
I know.
أنا أعرف.
Her head.
رأسها.
Shen Xiu's head...
رأس شين شيو...
Magistrate Jiang Chun was the one who found it.
القاضي جيانغ تشون هو من عثر عليه.
Jiang Chun?
جيانغ تشون؟
(Young Jiang Chun) Who said you could come here?
(يونغ جيانغ تشون) من قال لك أن تأتي إلى هنا؟
I found
لقد وجدت
her head.
رأسها.
You may rise.
يمكنك النهوض.
I found the head of the dead person.
لقد وجدت رأس الشخص الميت.
Does that mean my father
هل هذا يعني والدي؟
can remain in the magistrate's office?
هل يمكن أن يبقى في مكتب القاضي؟
Although her head was completely rotten,
على الرغم من أن رأسها كان متعفناً تماماً،
it bore the imprint
لقد حملت البصمة
left by Li Ji's private seal.
تركها لي جي بختمه الخاص.
Thus, the evidence chain was complete.
وهكذا اكتملت سلسلة الأدلة.
That was how he was sentenced to death.
هكذا حُكم عليه بالإعدام.
Imprinting one's private seal onto a rotten human head?
هل يُعقل نقش ختم المرء الخاص على رأس بشري متعفن؟
This method of slander
هذا أسلوب من أساليب التشهير
is utterly despicable!
إنه أمرٌ حقيرٌ للغاية!
Since you don't like to be a human,
بما أنك لا تحب أن تكون إنسانًا،
and you like to be an animal,
وأنت تحب أن تكون حيواناً،
you can enjoy being an animal.
يمكنك الاستمتاع بكونك حيواناً.
(The 6th day of the 5th month, 9th year of Zhenghe)
(اليوم السادس من الشهر الخامس، السنة التاسعة من عام تشنغخه)
(I wonder if the rain has stopped?)
(أتساءل إن كان المطر قد توقف؟)
(The weather conditions are unknown.)
(الأحوال الجوية غير معروفة.)
(12 days until the 7th day of the 6th month)
(12 يومًا حتى اليوم السابع من الشهر السادس)
Jiang Chun.
جيانغ تشون.
♪A thrush's song pierced the endless night♪
???اخترق غناء طائر الشحرور الليل الذي لا ينتهي؟؟؟
♪Blood splattered on the bamboo cage, reflecting the cool moonlight♪
تناثر الدم على قفص الخيزران، عاكساً ضوء القمر البارد.
♪Thirteen years of frost and snow sealed the old study window♪
???أغلقت ثلاثة عشر عاماً من الصقيع والثلج نافذة غرفة الدراسة القديمة؟
♪I twisted the needle, prying open the past♪
???لويت الإبرة، وفتحت الماضي على مصراعيه؟
♪A cold stone marrow presses against my palm♪
يضغط نخاع حجري بارد على راحة يدي.
♪My older brother lay buried afar♪
أخي الأكبر مدفون في مكان بعيد.
♪Flames licked across that place♪
??? امتدت ألسنة اللهب عبر ذلك المكان ???
♪A list of righteous hearts♪
قائمة بالقلوب الصالحة
♪Who laughed in the dark at the panic?♪
من الذي ضحك في الظلام على الذعر؟
♪I'm the shadow caged within as well as the flying light♪
أنا الظل المحبوس في الداخل، وكذلك الضوء الطائر.
♪Only when hatred burns out did we know how scorching our obsessions were♪
لم ندرك مدى اشتعال هواجسنا إلا عندما انطفأت جذوة الكراهية.
♪You said you'd die if you hit a stone♪
قلتَ إنك ستموت إذا اصطدمت بحجر؟
♪Yet you crashed into my fate's web♪
ومع ذلك، فقد وقعتَ في شباك قدري؟
♪Pear blossoms fell all over the wound on your shoulder♪
سقط زهر الكمثرى على الجرح الموجود على كتفك.
♪The wind in the bamboo forest dispersed the hexagrams♪
??? هبّت الرياح في غابة الخيزران فشتتت الأشكال السداسية ???
♪The thrush carried the past away♪
حمل طائر السمنة الماضي بعيدًا.
♪I stood at the end of the fireworks and gaze♪
وقفتُ في نهاية الألعاب النارية ونظرتُ إليها.
♪You lifted a lantern to illuminate♪
رفعتَ فانوسًا لتنيره.
♪That page♪
تلك الصفحة؟